<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: onramp-services | The fastest and smoothest way to good architecture]]></title>
  <link href="http://hwyfwk.com/blog/categories/onramp-services/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hwyfwk.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-10-27T18:12:53-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://hwyfwk.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Tim Rayburn & Devlin Liles]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[Team@HwyFwk.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Performance Testing Queries]]></title>
    <link href="http://hwyfwk.com/blog/2013/10/27/performance-testing-queries/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-27T16:31:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://hwyfwk.com/blog/2013/10/27/performance-testing-queries</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When dealing with data access you should always adhere to Jackson&rsquo;s rules of optimization. For convenience they are right here:</p>

<h3>M.A. Jackson (Principles of Program Design, 1975) wrote:</h3>

<p><strong>Rule 1.</strong> Don&rsquo;t do it</p>

<p><strong>Rule 2. (for experts only)</strong> Don&rsquo;t do it yet.</p>

<p>Performance optimization should only be done when needed, but when you need to it should be easy to execute and to measure. With this in mind, Highway took some of the heavy lifting out of the hands of the developers. This is normally the tools that we will use to identify a query that is not performing up to par so we can change it. Let&rsquo;s take the previous example of deleting all cars of a certain make.</p>

<h1>Example Domain</h1>

<p>In all of the examples below, we&rsquo;ll be working with the following business domain, from our Driver&rsquo;s Education company:</p>

<p>```
public class Car
{</p>

<pre><code>public int Id { get; set; }
public string Make { get; set; }
public string Model { get; set; }
public string Year { get; set; }
</code></pre>

<p>}</p>

<p>public class DropMake : Command
{</p>

<pre><code>public DropMake(string make)
{
    // THIS IS A REALLY BAD WAY TO REMOVE MULTIPLE ROWS
    // IT WOULD NORMALLY BE MUCH BETTER TO USE AN
    // AdvancedCommand TO PERFORM THIS TYPE OF OPERATION
    ContextQuery = c =&gt;
    {
        var cars = c.AsQueryable&lt;Car&gt;().Where(car =&gt; car.Make == make);
        foreach (var car in cars)
        {
            c.Remove(car);
        }
    };
}
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>

<h1>Performance Tests</h1>

<h2>These should <em>ideally</em> run against production like data</h2>

<p>I am going to use a command for delete, but this could be just as easily done with a <code>Scalar</code> or <code>Query</code>.</p>

<p>We want to measure the time it takes to execute the query and measure it against our maximum. If you cannot define a specific maximum for the test, you should look at Jackson rule 1. If your maximum doesn&rsquo;t fail this test, look at Jackson rule 2.</p>

<p>```
[TestMethod]
public void ShouldDeleteInUnder250Milliseconds()
{</p>

<pre><code>var context = new DataContext(Settings.Default.Connection, new DataMappings());

var dropMake = new DropMake("Chevy");

dropMake.RunPerformanceTest(context,false,250);
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>

<p>If the time exceeds maximum the performance test will throw an exception which will fail the test. The time and expected are in the exception.</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s take a closer look at this line
<code>
dropMake.RunPerformanceTest(context,false,250);
</code>
The 1st parameter, context, is the data connection we use to execute the test.</p>

<p>The 2nd parameter, false, is a flag telling us to include the start up time of the context in the total time. This is useful with ORMs like Entity Framework or NHibernate that have a large one time cost on start up. We give you the option of excluding that time from your evaluation.</p>

<p>The 3rd parameter, 250, is the total milliseconds allowed for the execution. If it exceeds this the test fails.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Roadmaps]]></title>
    <link href="http://hwyfwk.com/blog/2013/10/19/roadmaps/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-19T08:38:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://hwyfwk.com/blog/2013/10/19/roadmaps</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Below is the current road map for the Highway Framework. All of these are subject to change, but we want to be as transparent as possible in planning so that we can gather input from the community. Any project not in the list is considered stable and not in need of changes in the next 6 months.</p>

<!-- MORE -->


<h1>Highway.Data</h1>

<h2>vNext &ndash; Time line &ndash; Q4 2013</h2>

<ul>
<li>By end of the year all features release to have written tutorials, and the API to have updated documentation</li>
<li>By end of the year EF 6.0 major features that need additional work in the framework will be supported and documented</li>
</ul>


<h2>vNext + 1 &ndash; Time line &ndash; Q1 2014</h2>

<ul>
<li>Context and Repository will have factories for creation that control lifetime of the objects</li>
<li>Projection based Scalars &ndash; Scalars will be converted to projection based to allow for SQL output,</li>
<li>Documentation &ndash; Video Tutorials for 80% features</li>
</ul>


<h1>Highway.Insurance</h1>

<h2>vNext &ndash; Time line &ndash; Q4 2013</h2>

<ul>
<li>By end of the year all features release to have written tutorials, and the API to have updated documentation</li>
<li>Version Support for VS 2013 APIs</li>
</ul>


<h2>vNext + 1 &ndash; Time line &ndash; Q1 2014</h2>

<ul>
<li>Video Tutorials for 80% features</li>
</ul>


<h1>Highway.Pavement</h1>

<h2>vNext &ndash; Time line &ndash; Q4 2013</h2>

<ul>
<li>By end of the year all features release to have written tutorials, and the API to have updated documentation</li>
</ul>


<h1>Highway.MVC &ndash; New Project</h1>

<h2>vFirst &ndash; Time line &ndash; Q4 2013</h2>

<ul>
<li>Package a set of classes that allow for MVVM Model hydration to Knockout or Angular by default from MVC Model</li>
<li>All feature documentation and usage video tutorials</li>
</ul>


<h1>Highway.OnRamp.MVC.MVVM &ndash; New Project</h1>

<h2>vFirst &ndash; Time line &ndash; Q4 2013</h2>

<ul>
<li>OnRamp to drop MVVM wire up and folder structure into any MVC project &ndash; Even Existing</li>
<li>Video to walk through basic structure</li>
</ul>


<h1>Highway.OnRamp.MVC</h1>

<h2>vNext &ndash; Timeline &ndash; Q4 2013</h2>

<ul>
<li>Documentation of all current features (70%+ complete already)</li>
<li>Reorganize solution structure to move most inserted classes into an App_Infrastructure folder</li>
<li>Introduce default conventions for &ldquo;Post<em>&rdquo; and &ldquo;Get</em>&rdquo; actions to be limited to HttpPost and HttpGet respectively via Filter injection.</li>
</ul>


<h1>Highway.RoadCrew</h1>

<h2>vFirst</h2>

<ul>
<li>Implement all currently listed stories/issues to establish a great foundation</li>
<li>Document all those features on the website, as completed.</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
